T. J. Anderson Papers MS006
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
T. J. Anderson Papers
1980 -- 1989
1889 -- 2019
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Anderson, Thomas Jefferson (T.J.)
MS006
86.8 Linear Feet 77 boxes and 6 oversized folders
2 Artifact(s)
1 Digital Object(s)
1 Web sites
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in eight series: Honors and memorabilia; Subject files; Compositions by T. J. Anderson; Compositions by other composers; Recordings by other composers; Additional accessions; Website; and 2019 accessions.
Biographical / Historical
Thomas Jefferson (T.J.) Anderson (1928- ) was born August 17, 1928 in Coatesville, Pennsylvania, and has worked as a composer, professor, and musician both nationally and internationally. He began teaching as a Professor of Music at Tufts in 1972 and also served as the Chairman of the Department of Music at Tufts from 1972-1980. In 1978 he became the Austin Fletcher Professor of Music and in 1990 became Austin Fletcher Professor of Music Emeritus at Tufts.
Anderson began experimenting with music at a young age. He was classically trained in piano and violin but quickly took up the saxophone, drums, bass, and trumpet in his teen years. At that time he started learning about jazz and its musical traditions. He began playing professionally at the age of fourteen. Anderson continued the dual training in classical and contemporary music while studying at West Virginia State College where he earned his bachelor's degree in 1950. Up until that time Anderson had primarily focused on musical performance. However, while in graduate school at Pennsylvania State he discovered his passion for composition and consequently received a PhD from the University of Iowa in music composition in 1958. His composition teachers include George Ceiga, Philip Bezanson, Richard Hervig, and Darius Milhaud.
Anderson taught at a number of colleges and universities including West Virginia State College (1955-56), Langston University (1958-63), Tennessee State University (1963-1969), and Morehouse College (1971-1972). After teaching at Tufts University from 1972-1990, he moved on to numerous composer-in-residence and visiting professor positions across the country. He has also performed, taught, and worked as a composer in Brazil, Germany, France, Italy and Switzerland and other countries around the world. He has been awarded fellowships from the MacDowell Colony, the Djerassi Foundation, the National Humanities Center (their first composer), and acted as scholar-in-residence at the Rockefeller Center for the Creative Arts, Bellagio, Italy, among others.
Anderson has written over 80 works which range from operas and symphonies to chamber and vocal music. He often draws inspiration from the life stories of slaves, minstrels, abolitionists and war veterans. His three operas include his first opera "Soldier Boy, Soldier," inspired by the Vietnam War's effect on the inner-city Black community, "Treemonisha," an orchestration of Scott Joplin's famous ragtime work, and "Walker" which is based on the life of David Walker, a freed slave living in Boston in the early 19th century. Additionally he has composed works for the Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company and for the cellist Yo Yo Ma.
TJ is a founder and the first president of the National Black Music Caucus, he was elected to the American Academy of Arts and Letters (2005), and he received awards from the National Association for the Study and Performance of African music, the Music South Corporation's award for outstanding accomplishments in music composition and overall contributions to African-American music, as well as several honorary degrees.
Related Materials
MS133 Donald Sur manuscripts. Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University, Medford, MA.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of T. J. Anderson's handwritten and printed music scores, mostly handwritten research notes, and printed material from the 1960s to 2000. Also included is biographical material, CDs, audio cassettes, photographs, scrapbooks, clippings, awards, and a website. The primary focus of this collection is the handwritten music scores and the associated material used to help create and compose the music.
Faculty papers; Greater Boston arts; Music; Anderson, Thomas Jefferson (T.J.)
- Honors and memorabilia, 1889 -- 2007; 1960 -- 1990; MS006.001; 6.0 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains biographical materials, honors, awards, and posters collected by T. J. Anderson. Particularly important are materials honoring Anderson on his 50th and 60th birthdays. Because the material contains different formats and sizes, respective items were housed accordingly.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Awards and Honors, 1979 -- 2007; MS006.001.001
    - NAACP Boston chapter award, area of the arts, award, 1980; MS006.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    - Arna Bontemps symposium and celebration, talk to the music: A festival of community, plaque, 2004; MS006.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    - Lincoln University, plaque, 1982; MS006.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    - Senior faculty citation for outstanding service to the class and the community, Tufts University class of 1983, award, MS006.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    - Lincoln University, plaque, 1982; MS006.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    - Pennsylvania State University, distinguished alumnus, award and medal, 1990; MS006.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
    - National Association of Negro Musicians, distinguished achievement award, award, 1979; MS006.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
    - Music South Corporation, award for outstanding accomplishments in music composition and overall contributions to African-American music, award, 1990; MS006.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
    - The National Black Music Caucus, award for providing inspirational leadership in advancing the causes of black music educators, award, 1980; MS006.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
    - The National Black Music Caucus, honor for distinguished service to music and music education, award, 1997; MS006.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the study and performance of african music, certificate, 2007; MS006.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
    - National Association for the study and performance of African music, award, 2007; MS006.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
    - West Virginia State College, diploma, 1984; MS006.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
    - Pennsylvania State University and Penn State Alumni Assoication, citation, 1982; MS006.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
    - University of Iowa alumni assoication, award, 2006; MS006.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
    - [Relic from African meeting house], 1988; MS006.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
    - American Music Center, award, 2007; MS006.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia, 1889 -- 2007; MS006.001.002
    - 50th birthday concert, photographs, 1978; MS006.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    - 60th birthday-articles and letters, 1989; MS006.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
      Copies of Letter for Robert Shaw and Michael Tippett, Copies of Newspaper Articles (Boston Globe, Boston Herald, April 1 and March 31, 1989)
    - 60th birthday-celebration programs, 1989; MS006.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
    - 60th birthday-concet, 1989; MS006.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
    - 60th birthday-letters and birthday cards, 1988 -- 1989; MS006.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
    - 60th birthday-letter from Michael Tippett (original), 1989; MS006.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
    - 60th birthday-tributes, "tribute"poem by T.J. Anderson III, letter from Robert Shaw (original), letter from Michael Tippett (copy), newspaper clippings, 1989; MS006.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
    - [American Composers Alliance], 1965 -- 1974; MS006.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
      [1 of 2]
    - [American Composers Alliance], 1975; MS006.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
      [2 of 2]
    - ARNA Bontemps Symposium and Celebration, 2004; MS006.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
    - [Atlanta Symphony Orchestra, ticket], 1979; MS006.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
    - [Atlanta Symphony Orchestra, program], 1979; MS006.001.002.00012 (Box 2)
    - [Atlanta Symphony Orchestra, program], 1980; MS006.001.002.00013 (Box 2)
    - [American Music Center, program], 2007; MS006.001.002.00014 (Box 2)
    - A concert at the White House, program, 1978; MS006.001.002.00015 (Box 2)
    - Critical histories of four contemporary black composers, 1980; MS006.001.002.00016 (Box 2)
    - "Critical histories of four contemporary black composers" part 2: T.J. Anderson project no. geh-81-103 by Dr. Christine E. Oliver slides 1-12 box 1, 1980; MS006.001.002.00017 (Box 2)
      slides
    - "Critical histories of four contemporary black composers" part 2: T.J. Anderson project no. geh-81-103 bt Dr. Christine E. Oliver slides 12-36 box 2, 1980; MS006.001.002.00018 (Box 2)
    - "Critical histories of four contemporary black composers" part 2: T.J. Anderson project no. geh-81-103 by Dr. Christine E. Oliver slides 37-59 box 3, 1980; MS006.001.002.00019 (Box 2)
    - "Critical histories of four contemporary black composers" project no. geh-81-103 T.J. Anderson, 1980; MS006.001.002.00020 (Box 2)
    - Curriculum vitae, 1950 -- 1997; MS006.001.002.00021 (Box 2)
    - Diploma-Saint Augustine College, 1996; MS006.001.002.00022 (Box 2)
    - Diploma(copy)-West Virginia State College, 1984; MS006.001.002.00023 (Box 2)
    - Diploma/Professor Emeritus-Tufts College, 1990; MS006.001.002.00024 (Box 2)
    - Doctor of Musical Arts, honorary degree - Saint Augustine College, May 11 1996, MS006.001.002.00025 (Box 2)
    - Doctor of Philosophy degree - State University of Iowa, June 13 1958, MS006.001.002.00026 (Box 2)
    - In Memoriam: Thomas Jefferson Anderson, 1889 -- 1967; MS006.001.002.00027 (Box 2)
    - Life paid alumni member certificate to Phi Mu Alpha Sinfonia, June 28 1951, MS006.001.002.00028 (Box 2)
    - Lillian Liebner award-Tufts University, 1985; MS006.001.002.00029 (Box 2)
    - [Moorehouse College glee club, program], 1972; MS006.001.002.00030 (Box 2)
    - [Music in Europe and the United States; a history program], 1986; MS006.001.002.00031 (Box 2)
    - Musical style and compositional techniques in selected works of T.J. Anderson, 1979; MS006.001.002.00032 (Box 2)
    - Musical style and compositional techniques in selected works of T.J. Anderson, 1979; MS006.001.002.00033 (Box 2)
    - [Newspaper articles], 1980; MS006.001.002.00034 (Box 2)
    - Opera, blacks, and vietnam: getting a fix, 1983; MS006.001.002.00035 (Box 2)
      Includes audiocassette.
    - Penn State alumni fellow-"ten years of alumni fellows 1973-1982" with personal insert from Penn State alumni associaton staff, MS006.001.002.00036 (Box 2)
    - Phi Beta Kappa, certificate, 1977; MS006.001.002.00037 (Box 2)
    - Phi Beta Kappa, program, 1977; MS006.001.002.00038 (Box 2)
    - [Photographs], 2006; MS006.001.002.00039 (Box 2)
    - Photograph - T.J. Anderson with sisters Jean Anderson White and Ilanita Anderson Prince at the wall of respect, 2003; MS006.001.002.00040 (Box 2)
    - [Postcard], 1980; MS006.001.002.00041 (Box 2)
    - [Saint Augustine College], 1995; MS006.001.002.00042 (Box 2)
    - [Saint Augustine's College, program], 1996; MS006.001.002.00043 (Box 2)
    - [Saint Augustine's College, program], 1994; MS006.001.002.00044 (Box 2)
    - Singing the living tradition, 1993; MS006.001.002.00045 (Box 2)
    - Tribute to T.J. Anderson, Richard Dyer, The Boston Globe, 1978; MS006.001.002.00046 (Box 2)
    - Tufts University 124th commencement exercises, program, 1980; MS006.001.002.00047 (Box 2)
      Signed by Dizzy Gillespie
    - [University of Iowa, program], 2006; MS006.001.002.00048 (Box 2)
    - Distiunguished alumni awards, 2006; MS006.001.002.00049 (Box 2)
    - Up from the cane-breaks: an autobiography, 1950; MS006.001.002.00050 (Box 2)
    - Up from the cane-breaks: an autobiography, 1950; MS006.001.002.00051 (Box 2)
    - Veduto de borgo di bellaggio sur lago di como, 1980; MS006.001.002.00052 (Box 2)
    - Weekly minder, 1989; MS006.001.002.00053 (Box 2)
    - [West Virginia State College, program], 1984; MS006.001.002.00054 (Box 2)
    - Western Michigan University, black composters in America, program, 1977; MS006.001.002.00055 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook, 1925; MS006.001.002.00056 (Box 2)
    - Yearbook, 1940; MS006.001.002.00057 (Box 2)
  - Oversize Honors and Posters, 1965 -- 2007; MS006.001.003
    - American Music Center 2007 letter of distinction, MS006.001.009.00001 (Box 9)
    - The Boston music viva, 1965; MS006.001.009.00002 (Box 9)
      Two copies.
    - Composers in red sneakers, 1985; MS006.001.009.00003 (Box 9)
    - Hall of black achievement, 1991; MS006.001.009.00004 (Box 9)
    - Harlem Savoy and its influence on jazz, 1974; MS006.001.009.00005 (Box 9)
      Two posters.
    - Northwestern University School of Music presents a staged workshop of an important operatic work in progress Slip Knot, 2000; MS006.001.009.00006 (Box 9)
    - The Pennsylvania State University outstanding alumni series, 1982; MS006.001.009.00007 (Box 9)
    - Presidential Citation to T.J. Anderson, National Association for Equal Opportunity in higher education, 1987; MS006.001.009.00008 (Box 9)
    - Second annual Black Composers Project presents T.J. Anderson, 1979; MS006.001.009.00009 (Box 9)
    - T. J. Anderson a concert of his works to celebrate his 50th year, 1978; MS006.001.009.00010 (Box 9)
      Two copies. One is signed.
    - Videmus presents T. J. Anderson 60th birthday celebration concert, 1989; MS006.001.009.00011 (Box 9)
      Several copies.
    - Thomas Jefferson's minstrels, 1982; MS006.001.009.00012 (Box 9)
    - Western Michigan University, open lecture 'the ragtime revival' by T.J. Anderson, 1977; MS006.001.009.00013 (Box 9)
    - The world premiere of T.J. Anderson's Soldier Boy, Soldier, 1982; MS006.001.009.00014 (Box 9)
  - Scrapbooks, 1959 -- 1989; MS006.001.004
    - Scrapbook, 1959 -- 1964; MS006.001.010.00001 (Box 10)
    - Scrapbook, 1964 -- 1972; MS006.001.011.00001 (Box 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1973 -- 1975; MS006.001.011.00002 (Box 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1977 -- 1989; MS006.001.011.00003 (Box 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1982; MS006.001.011.00004 (Box 11)
- Subject Files, 1961 -- 2003; 1970 -- 1999; MS006.002; 7.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains subject files that cover T. J. Anderson's teaching and compositions as well as official and personal correspondence. Most material dates from his tenure as professor in the music department at Tufts University. Composition related material includes contracts and performance related correspondence. Research notes documenting the creative side of composing are found in Series III. Scores found in correspondence folders in this series were removed and placed in Series III; a copy of the score was left in the original folder.
  - Administration, 1996, MS006.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Administration, 1999 -- 2001; MS006.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Bellagio, Italy, 1983 -- 1984; MS006.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Black History Month Presentation, Edwards Middle School, Charlestown MA. Winchester Star, Feb 21, 1985; MS006.002.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Black Music Caucus, 1976 -- 1993; MS006.002.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - Boston Musica Viva Celebrates Black Composers. Boston Globe, Boston Herald, Feb 25, 1985; MS006.002.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - Brazil - CONFIDENTIAL, 1988; MS006.002.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Brazil - Notes, 1976; MS006.002.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Center for Black Music Research Project, 1986 -- 1987; MS006.002.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Center for Black Music Research Repertory Ensemble, 1988 -- 1990; MS006.002.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Composers Concert Series - Tufts, 1975 -- 1985; MS006.002.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1961 -- 1972; MS006.002.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1973; MS006.002.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1975 -- 1976; MS006.002.003.00014 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1975 -- 1976; MS006.002.003.00015 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1974 -- 1978; MS006.002.003.00016 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1978 -- 1979; MS006.002.003.00017 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1979 -- 1980; MS006.002.003.00018 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1981, MS006.002.003.00019 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1981 -- 1982; MS006.002.003.00020 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1982 -- 1983; MS006.002.003.00021 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1983 -- 1984; MS006.002.003.00022 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1984 -- 1985; MS006.002.003.00023 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1985 -- 1986; MS006.002.003.00024 (Box 3)
  - Composition, 1986 -- 1987; MS006.002.003.00025 (Box 3)
  - Composition, Spring 1987, MS006.002.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - Composition, Fall, 1987; MS006.002.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1987-Spring 1988, 1987 -- 1988; MS006.002.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1988 -- 1989; MS006.002.004.00004 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1989; MS006.002.004.00005 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1989 -- 1990; MS006.002.004.00006 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1990 -- 1991; MS006.002.004.00007 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1990 -- 1991; MS006.002.004.00008 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1991; MS006.002.004.00009 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1993; MS006.002.004.00010 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1994; MS006.002.004.00011 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1996; MS006.002.004.00012 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1997; MS006.002.004.00013 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1998; MS006.002.004.00014 (Box 4)
  - Composition, 1999; MS006.002.004.00015 (Box 4)
  - DeLerma, Dominique-Rene, 1975 -- 1983; MS006.002.004.00016 (Box 4)
  - Djerassi, Summer, 1988 -- 1989; MS006.002.004.00017 (Box 4)
  - Dream Realized/Nightmare Resolved: A Dissertation Proposal by William C. Banfield (autographed), 1988; MS006.002.004.00018 (Box 4)
  - Echoes, 1987 -- 1992; MS006.002.005.00001 (Box 5)
  - Echoes, 1988 -- 1992; MS006.002.005.00002 (Box 5)
  - Ethnicity in America Program - Speaker, Tufts University, Dec 3, 1983, MS006.002.005.00003 (Box 5)
  - "The First Decade of the Black Music Caucus" by Camille Clemeneau Taylor, with photograph, 1986; MS006.002.005.00004 (Box 5)
  - Hunt, Richard (sculptor), 1968 -- 2000; MS006.002.005.00005 (Box 5)
  - Inauguration Piece, 1981; MS006.002.005.00006 (Box 5)
  - Lectures and Visiting Professorships, 1988 -- 1998; MS006.002.005.00007 (Box 5)
  - "Making History" with Personal Card, n.d., MS006.002.005.00008 (Box 5)
    No Date Available
  - Meet the Composer, 1981 -- 1987; MS006.002.005.00009 (Box 5)
  - Memphis Piano Summit, 1979 -- 1982; MS006.002.005.00010 (Box 5)
  - Memphis Symphony Orchestra Program with Newspaper Clippings from The Commercial Appeal, 1987; MS006.002.005.00011 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1971 -- 1991; MS006.002.005.00012 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1972 -- 1973; MS006.002.005.00013 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1973 -- 1986; MS006.002.005.00014 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1975; MS006.002.005.00015 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1975 -- 1976; MS006.002.005.00016 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1975 -- 1977; MS006.002.005.00017 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1976 -- 1977; MS006.002.005.00018 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1979; MS006.002.005.00019 (Box 5)
  - Personal, 1979 -- 1980; MS006.002.006.00001 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1978 -- 1980; MS006.002.006.00002 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1980 -- 1982; MS006.002.006.00003 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1981; MS006.002.006.00004 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1981 -- 1982; MS006.002.006.00005 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1982 -- 1983; MS006.002.006.00006 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1982 -- 1983; MS006.002.006.00007 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1983 -- 1984; MS006.002.006.00008 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1984; MS006.002.006.00009 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1984 -- 1985; MS006.002.006.00010 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1985; MS006.002.006.00011 (Box 6)
  - Personal, Fall 1985, MS006.002.006.00012 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1985 -- 1986; MS006.002.006.00013 (Box 6)
  - Personal, 1986 -- 1987; MS006.002.006.00014 (Box 6)
  - Personal, Spring 1987, MS006.002.007.00001 (Box 7)
  - Personal, Fall 1987, MS006.002.007.00002 (Box 7)
  - Personal, Spring 1988, MS006.002.007.00003 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1988; MS006.002.007.00004 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1988 -- 1989; MS006.002.007.00005 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1989; MS006.002.007.00006 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1994; MS006.002.007.00007 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1996; MS006.002.007.00008 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1997; MS006.002.007.00009 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1998; MS006.002.007.00010 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1999; MS006.002.007.00011 (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1999 -- 2001; MS006.002.008.00001 (Box 8)
  - Personal Letters from Fellow Artists, 1961 -- 1972; MS006.002.008.00002 (Box 8)
  - Pierce, Chester, 1975 -- 1984; MS006.002.008.00003 (Box 8)
  - Programs, Articles, and Flyers, 1972 -- 1980; MS006.002.008.00004 (Box 8)
  - Programs, Articles, and Flyers, 1972 -- 1988; MS006.002.008.00005 (Box 8)
  - Sea of Stars, Fanfare Invitation, 1986; MS006.002.008.00006 (Box 8)
  - Shell Fairy Notes, MS006.002.008.00007 (Box 8)
  - Singleton, Alvin, 1978 -- 1987; MS006.002.008.00008 (Box 8)
  - Slavery Documents 2, 2001 -- 2003; MS006.002.008.00009 (Box 8)
  - Spirituals, 1979 -- 1982; MS006.002.008.00010 (Box 8)
  - Symposium on Black American Music, Information Forum, Ann Arbor, Michigan, Aug 9-16 1985, MS006.002.008.00011 (Box 8)
  - Thompson, Leon - N.Y. Philharmonic, 1974 -- 1983; MS006.002.008.00012 (Box 8)
  - A Tribute to Harold Arlen, "What Time Is It?", Program Included, NY Times, 1986; MS006.002.008.00013 (Box 8)
  - Tufts Daily, MS006.002.008.00014 (Box 8)
  - Tufts Music Department 100th Birthday, 1995; MS006.002.008.00015 (Box 8)
  - Videmus, 1988 -- 1992; MS006.002.008.00016 (Box 8)
  - Virginia Center for the Creative Arts, 1989 -- 1992; MS006.002.008.00017 (Box 8)
  - Wilson, Olly - International Dictionary of Black Composers, CBMR, 1995 -- 1996; MS006.002.008.00018 (Box 8)
  - Wonderful Teacher, Jan 1984, MS006.002.008.00019 (Box 8)
  - Work, John Memorial Foundation, 1974 -- 1978; MS006.002.008.00020 (Box 8)
- Compositions by T.J. Anderson, 1956 -- 2004; 1975 -- 2004; MS006.003; 18.25 Linear Feet
  This series contains original scores and recordings by T.J. Anderson as well as associated material. A majority of the scores are handwritten manuscripts on paper or onion skin while the rest are printed copies. Some folders include scores and individual instruments parts. Secondary material consists of librettos, handwritten research notes, source material, and correspondence. The Digital Collections and Archives do not hold the copyright for any of T.J. Anderson's works.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - 5 bagatelles for oboe, violin, and harpsichord, 1963; MS006.003.012.00001 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)
    Handwritten manuscript(score); oboe, violin, harpsichord.
  - 5 easy pieces, 1974; MS006.003.012.00002 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)
    Handwritten manuscript(score); violin, piano, jew's harp.
  - 6 pieces for clarinet and chamber orchestra, 1962; MS006.003.012.00003 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)
    Handwritten manuscript(score);clarinet, chamber orchestra.
  - 7 cabaret songs, 1994; MS006.003.012.00004 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)
    Handwritten manuscript(score); text: Harryette Mullen; jazz singer, flute, viola, cello, piano; associated material can be found at MS006/003-032#00001.
  - Ancestral voices, 1990; MS006.003.012.00005 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)
    Handwritten manuscript(score); text: Leon Forrest; bass voice, and piano
  - And death shall have no dominion, 1980; MS006.003.012.00006 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)
    This date is approximate; handwritten manuscript(score); chorus.
  - Aurelia, in memoriam, 1999; MS006.003.012.00007 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)
    Handwritten manuscript, handwritten onion skins, copy; solo violin.
  - B bop in 2, 1998; MS006.003.012.00008 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)
    Handwritten manuscript (alta sax); alto sax and two recorders.
  - Bahia, brasil, 1990; MS006.003.012.00009 (Box Large Map Case 2 Drawer 9)